Preliminary Inventory to the East Timor and Indonesia Action Network Records TAM.393
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
East Timor and Indonesia Action Network Records
1993-2005
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
East Timor and Indonesia Action Network/U.S.
Miller, John M.
TAM.393
13 Linear Feet (13 boxes)
The East Timor Action Network (ETAN) was founded in November 1991 to support self-determination and human rights for the people of East Timor (Timor-Leste). While the national headquarters are in New York City, there are also some two dozen chapters around the United States. After East Timor achieved independence from Indonesia in 2002, ETAN changed (in 2005) its name (but not its acronym) to East Timor and Indonesia Action Network, to better reflect its goals of supporting human rights, justice, and democracy in both East Timor and Indonesia. The records contain clippings, U.S. Congressional documents, correspondence, financial records, press releases, subject files, and audiovisual materials, most relating to the operations of the national organization.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials donated by John M. Miller, National Coordinator for the East Timor and Indonesia Action Network (ETAN), in 2007. The accession number associated with this gift is 2007.011.
Arrangement
Files are in original order; the collection is unprocessed, but content summaries exist for boxes 1-13.
Organized into six series
Missing Title
I. Congressional Material
II. Financial and Administrative
III. Subject Files
IV. Press Releases
V. Clippings
VI. Miscellaneous (Related Organizations, Articles, Audiocassettes and DVDs)
Historical/Biographical Note
The East Timor Action Network (ETAN) was founded in November 1991 to support self-determination and human rights for the people of East Timor (Timor-Leste) in accordance with the Universal Declaration of Human Rights, and Security Council and General Assembly resolutions on East Timor. While its national headquarters are in New York City, there are also some two dozen chapters around the United States. ETAN's primary focus has been to change US foreign policy and raise public awareness to support justice and self-determination and now genuine independence for East Timor (which became an independent country in 2002), and human rights in Indonesia. In 2005 ETAN changed its name to the East Timor and Indonesia Action Network (although it retained the same acronym, ETAN) to better reflect its goals of supporting rights, justice, and democracy in both East Timor and Indonesia. ETAN works for justice for historic and ongoing crimes against humanity, war crimes, and human rights violations in East Timor and Indonesia.
Colonized by Portugal in the sixteenth century, East Timor was known as Portuguese Timor until November, 1975, when East Timor declared its independence from Portugal. Nine days later, it was invaded and occupied by Indonesian forces before the declaration could be internationally recognised. Indonesia alleged that the popular East Timorese FRETILIN party was communist. The United States supported the Indonesian government's actions. The East Timorese guerrilla force, Falintil, fought a campaign against the Indonesian forces from 1975 to 1999. Amnesty International estimated that during Indonesia's occupation, some 200,000 "excess deaths," mainly from hunger and illness. Following the UN-sponsored act of self-determination that year, Indonesia relinquished control of the territory and East Timor became the first new country of the twenty-first century in 2002. Alongside the Philippines, East Timor is one of only two predominantly Roman Catholic countries in Asia, and the only Portuguese-speaking sovereign state in Asia.
Sources:
For more information see the ETAN website (http://etan.org/etan/default.htm).
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Richard W. Franke Files on Indonesia and East Timor (TAM 590)
Scope and Content Note
The records contain clippings, correspondence, financial and administrative records, press releases, subject files, U.S. Congressional materials, and audiovisual materials, principally documenting the activity of the national organization. For more detailed information, see the descriptions in the container list, below. NOTE: This collection is housed offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Timor-Leste |x Foreign public opinion, American.; Timor-Leste |x History |x Autonomy and independence movements.; Clippings (information artifacts); Human rights |z Indonesia.; Human rights |z Timor-Leste.; Audiovisual materials.; Government records; Timor-Leste.; Correspondence.; Financial records; Press releases.; East Timor and Indonesia Action Network/U.S.; Miller, John M.
- Series I: Congressional Materials.
  - Congressional Material 1. Contains: Legislation / Congress Discussion 2000-2005; Statements to the Congress – include: Madeleine Albright, Bill Luther, Chris Smith, Cynthia A. McKenney; Congressional Addresses 1997, 1995-2005 (Box 1, Folder data_value_missing_f7ccd90aa7f17c07c60bcdc2df0dfc08)
  - Congressional Material 2. Contains: Hearings, Testimonies Before the House of Representatives (includes Aryati, R.M. Gadbaw, Manuel dos Martires); Petitions to the Congress; Congressional Correspondence (includes: letters to ETAN members, Patrick Kennedy, Ali Alatas and many others); Clinton's, Albright's, Kofi Anan's correspondence; ETAN's correspondence, 1998-2000 (Box 2, Folder data_value_missing_cebf8895b6b47d23accced530cac5f4d)
- Series II: Financial and Administrative Records.
  - ETAN. Contains: Correspondence; Grant Applications; Fliers, Brochures of Events; Bios, Personnel Issues; Trip to Timor 1995, 2003; Documents (include Lease, Information Packages, Retreat Minutes, Annual Reports); Other East Timor Groups; Fliers of Events organized by other East Timor Groups (Box 3, Folder data_value_missing_9ee4209f8ed229deda07beee0eb08889)
  - EAST TIMOR - FINANCIAL SUPPORT. Contains: Lobby Days (information packages, documents, participants); Donor Meetings; Transition Support Program (TSP); Trust Fund for East Timor; International Financial Institutes (reports, fact sheets, donor supervision, budgets); World Bank; USAID, 1997-2005 (Box 4, Folder data_value_missing_024a64ba00e1cca5905f618aaef10a32)
- Series III: Subject Files.
  - Subject Files A – D. Contains: Action Alerts; America Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organization; Amnesty International; Arms Control Legislation; Asian Women's Shelter Asian Pacific Conference; Burma; CAVR Public Hearing; Campaign for Labor Rights / Nike; Covert Action; Catholic Church; Demilitarization; Democracy NOW!, 1993-2005 (Box 5, Folder data_value_missing_02844bc365e9373ae0279bee2e740d93)
  - Subject Files E – H. Contains: Episcopal Church; East Timor Human Rights Centre (ETHRC); East Timor related materials: Civil Society, Cocoa, Coffee, Constitution, Culture, Education, Election, Environment, Fact Sheets, Government, Health Policy, Websites; Exxon Mobil Lawsuit; Foreign Policy; Grassroots; Heritage Foundation; Human Rights Watch, 1995-2004 (Box 6, Folder data_value_missing_da86dacd331eebef742421183395aaa6)
  - Subject Files I – L. Contains: Independence Celebration / East Timor; Indonesia (Democracy, Info Packets, Human Rights Network; Military; OTI; Terrorism; Working Groups; World Bank); Initiatives for International Dialogues; International Federation for East Timor: Legislative, Human Rights Units; International Fellowship Statement; International Republican Institute (IRI); International Tribunal and Accountability; Judicial Systems Monitoring Program: The Future of the Serious Crimes Unit; Labor / Employment – KSTL Labor Organization Jakarta; Kondfederasaun Sindikatu Timor Lorosa (KSTL) / Labor Organization; La'o Hamutuk: Institute for Renconstruction Monitoring and Analysis; Laskar, Jihad: Indonesian Terrorist Lumintang, Johnny: Indonesian General; Lustrilanang, Pius: Indonesian student movement leader, 1999-2005 (Box 7, Folder data_value_missing_6236ac3607ea331b1432b2db288f224b)
  - Subject Files O – Ra. Contains: Massachusetts Burma Case; Military (Issues, Reports, Trainings, Other Countries); New Administration; NGO correspondence; Oil; Peace Action; Police Training; Political Prisoners (Correspondence, ETHRC, Indonesia); Portuguese Caucuses, Conference Purchasing Laws; Pinto, Constancio: member of Timorese Resistance, Representative of the National Council of Maubere Resistance (CNRM) to the UN; Ramos-Horta, José: founder member of Revolutionary Front for an Independent East Timor, Nobel Prize winner (1996), currently the Prime Minister of East Timor, 1996-2004 (Box 8, Folder data_value_missing_2104ffb556abd00ec7d178913df7e289)
  - Subject Files Re – W. Contains: Refugees; Referendums (U.S. Government, UNAMET, UN, AI, Pre-Vote Military); Relief Development Programs; Religious Resolutions; Research Papers; Roth, Stanley: Assistant Secretary for East Asian and Pacific Affairs; Department of State / Hearings; School of Advanced International Studies, DC – Conference; Self-Determination Struggles; Student Demonstrations; TAPOL, the Indonesian Human Rights Campaign; Timika; Torture; UN: Decolonalization Committee: Mission in East Timor (UNAMET); High Commissioner for Human Rights (UNHCR); Report on Violence against Women; USAID; U.S. East Timor Society West Timor; White House (briefings, correspondence); Youth Urgent Appeal, 1997-2001 (Box 9, Folder data_value_missing_fda8ccd23a280e126913d0922c0aff30)
- Series IV: Press Releases.
  - Press Releases and Statements issued by ETAN, Reuters, TAPOL, Congressmen (Kennedy, P.; Pelosi, N.; Reed, J.), Ramos-Horta, etc., 1997-2005 (Box 10, Folder data_value_missing_8af79dac2cd405169f070d1524ab9096)
- Series V: Clippings.
  - Clippings, 1994-2005 (Box 11, Folder data_value_missing_53d23475ddc762950525a64a22552459)
- Series VI: Miscellaneous (Includes Related Organizations, Articles, Audiocassettes and DVDs).
  - Published Articles, Brochures, Booklets, Audio Cassettes and DVD's. Contains (Topics): Aceh, East Timor, Indonesia, Jakarta, Women's Question; Contains (Organizations): Amnesty International, Asian-Pacific Coalition for East-Timor, East Timor Alert Network, East Timor Support Center, International Alert, Indonesia Alert, National Democratic Institute, U.S. Committee for Refugees, 1993-2000 (Box 12)
  - Documents on East Timor from PeaceNet and Connected Computer Network (a periodical published by ETAN) Volumes 21-43., 1993-1996 (Box 13)